<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Early years childcare</title>
    <description>A major project looking at the sustainability of childcare provision in the UK
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/early-years-project/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/early-years-project/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 11:27:02 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 11:27:02 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>EXPLAINER: What is free entitlement?</title>
        <description>&lt;html&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; Free entitlement &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funding early years education can be a little complicated. This explainer will take a look at free entitlement, a government scheme to allow free childcare. The scheme covers children ranging from two-year-olds to three-and-four-year-olds. But how does it all work?
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Listen to this post&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;audio controls=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/early-years-project/assets/audio/free-entitlement.mp3&quot;&gt; &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; What is free entitlement? &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it states in the name, free entitlement means that parents can get a certain amount of free childcare. Early years settings can offer entitlement places that parents can take up if they are eligible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; How much entitlement can you get? &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt; The number of free hours a child can receive is usually 15 hours. This applies to children who are two and also between three and four. But, back in September 2017, a new government scheme launched allowing parents to get &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/thousands-of-parents-benefit-from-30-hours-free-childcare-early&quot;&gt; double the number of free entitlement hours&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three to four-year-olds in England can get 570 free hours per year. During the school term time, parents can get 30 hours of free childcare per week for 38 weeks of the year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; This scheme of 30 hours free entitlement has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/money/2017/feb/08/introduction-of-30-hours-free-childcare-could-mean-shortage-of-places&quot;&gt;under scrutiny&lt;/a&gt; since it was introduced. Childcare providers have raised concerns over sustainability and affordability.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&quot;/early-years-project/assets/article_images/fence.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The 30 hours of entitlement requires additional funding to cover the cost and also settings need to ensure they have a sufficient number of available employees to staff it. Picture source: Pixabay.&quot; /&gt;
  

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who is eligible for the scheme? &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt; For two-year-old free entitlement, parents must receive one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Income Support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Income based Job Seekers’ Allowance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Income related Employment and Support Allowance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State Pension Credit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universal Credit (with an annual net income of no more than £15,400)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tax Credits (with an annual gross income of no more than £16,190)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working Tax Credit 4-week run on (the payment you get when you stop qualifying for Working Tax Credit)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support through 'part 6' under the Immigration and Asylum Act (NASS support)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Children can also be eligible if they are looked after by the local authority, have an education, health and care plan, are in receipt of disability living allowance or have left care through special guardianship or an adoption or residence order. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; How can I apply? &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To check if you are available for free entitlement, the government has an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/apply-30-hours-free-childcare&quot;&gt;application process&lt;/a&gt;. Parents can enter details and see what entitlement is available to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&quot;/early-years-project/assets/article_images/childcare-application.png&quot; alt=&quot;This website is where parents can apply for entitlement. Screengrab took from the official government website. Access the website via: https://www.gov.uk/apply-30-hours-free-childcare&quot; /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; How will I know if my application has been approved? &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Once you have applied and are successful, you will receive a code. This code will grant you 30 hours of free childcare which you need to give to your childcare provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where can I find free entitlement providers?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via the government website, you can search for pre-school and nurseries to see what early childcare and education is available. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/find-free-early-education?step-by-step-nav=f237ec8e-e82c-4ffa-8fba-2a88a739783b&quot;&gt;search page&lt;/a&gt; allows you to find nursery school places and registered childminders. There are different schemes for Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; How long do I get entitlement for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt; When your child is two or between the ages of three and four. Most children after their fourth birthday will start school in September meaning they leave the early years setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A child to start later, but they must be in full-time education by the time they reach ‘compulsory school age'. This is on 31 December, 31 March or 31 August following their fifth birthday, whichever comes first.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 12:34:25 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/early-years-project/2021/06/23/what-is-free-entitlement.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/early-years-project/2021/06/23/what-is-free-entitlement.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
